י"ז עמוד א' Yud zayin amud aleph now top of the page,
the משנה. Mishnah. דם השרץ והבשר מצטרפין זה עם זה. Dam HaSheretz
v'HaBassar mitztarfin ze im ze. So now we are clearly dealing with
טומאה, tumah, not clearly, but we are. Anyway, if you have the
blood of a שרץ sheretz and the meat of a שרץ sheretz
they combine for the minimum size. We already learned that שרצים shratzim
is כעדשה. ke'adasha. Okay, so you have a little bit of blood
and a little bit of the flesh. They make the minimum size
in order to cause that טומאה. tumah. כלל אמר רבי יהושע, Klall
amar Rabbi Yehoshua, here's a principle that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said:
כל שטומאתו ושיעורו שוין מצטרפין. Kol shetumato v'shiuro shavin mitztarfin. If the
degree of טומאה tumah and the amount are equal, then they combine.
טומאתו ולא שיעורו שיעורו ולא טומאתו. Tumato v'lo shiuro, shiuro v'lo tumato.
Let's say the טומאה tumah is the same,
the weightiness of the טומאה tumah but not the amount. What would
be an example of this? So let's say, for example, a שרץ
sheretz causes טומאה tumah and it's an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, and
a נבילה, neveilah, a dead cow, causes טומאה tumah and it's an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. But we just learned that a נבילה neveilah
goes by כזית kezayit and a שרץ sheretz goes by כעדשה. ke'adasha.
So if you have a little bit of נבילה neveilah and a
little bit of שרץ sheretz they don't combine even though you could
say perhaps a שרץ sheretz is more potent, so a little שרץ
sheretz gets you up to the כזית kezayit you need for a
נבילה. neveilah. No, they are fundamentally different categories and you cannot combine
across categories. That's טומאתו ולא שיעורו. tumato v'lo shiuro. Similarly, שיעורו ולא
טומאתו. shiuro v'lo tumato. Let's say the שיעור shiur is the same
but not the טומאה. tumah. A כזית kezayit of a מת, met,
a corpse, and a כזית kezayit of a נבילה, neveilah, both cause
טומאה. tumah. Let's say you combine a half of a כזית kezayit
of each. Again, you could say a corpse is much more potent,
but no, because it is a different type of טומאה. tumah. A
corpse is called an אבי אבות הטומאה. avi avot hatumah. Somebody who
touches a corpse is an אב, av, somebody who touches a נבילה
neveilah is a ראשון. rishon. So the מת met is a higher
level, causes seven days טומאה tumah and so on. So therefore it
does not combine with a נבילה neveilah even for the lesser of
the טומאה. tumah.
And
so the whole reason we're doing שרצים shratzim is because we're talking
about מצטרפין. mitztarfin.
The first משנה Mishnah was about מצטרפין, mitztarfin, now we're on a
מצטרפין mitztarfin focus.
Okay, and the place where like these things... this is a primary
place where these...
There's sometimes they're cross-referenced in other places but yeah, I mean, as
I said before, often these collections are early collections of משניות mishnayot
and they don't sort of fit a theme as much as, you
know, in terms of like topic as much as they do in
terms of like the formal structure of them. Okay, it's like the
A-B-s. Okay. כל שטומאתו ושיעורו, Kol shetumato v'shiuro, okay, טומאתו ולא שיעורו
שיעורו ולא טומאתו. Tumato v'lo shiuro, shiuro v'lo tumato. Okay, so the
שיעור shiur and the טומאה tumah is the same, not the טומאה
tumah like a מת met and a נבילה, neveilah, or לא טומאתו
ולא שיעורו. lo tumato v'lo shiuro. That's the most obvious, like a
מת met and a שרץ, sheretz, right? Both different sizes and different
degrees of טומאה. tumah. אין מצטרפין, ein mitztarfin, those don't combine. What
you need to have is the same size and the same degree
of טומאה. tumah. Now even that is a חידוש, chidush, right? To
think that things at the same size and the same degree are
combined because you could still say they're fundamentally different טומאות tumot even
if it's the same potency and the same amount.
Now I don't... Okay, so I don't know if there actually is
a case of where you actually cross category, where across different categories
you have the same size but different... the same size and the
same potency but fundamentally different categories. You have different נבילות, neveilot, you
have different שרצים. shratzim.
Nothing would combine with a מת. met.
Would there anything be like a נבילה neveilah which would be a
כזית? kezayit? I don't know, I'd have to think of it. I
don't know of anything. I mean, that would be the most interesting
if you could get something that satisfied same degree of טומאה tumah
and same שיעור shiur but was fundamentally a different type of a
טומאה. tumah.
You
have...
like let's say the טומאה tumah of a non-kosher animal which is
not...
but those are all נבילה neveilah טומאה. tumah.
Yeah, I don't know. And then after you get beyond נבילה, neveilah,
מת, met, and שרץ, sheretz, they're all much more about human טומאות,
tumot, right? About זב zav and זבה, zavah, מצורע, metzora, whatever. I
mean you have the spit of a זב zav and let's say
the spit of a זבה. zavah. Is that what... and let's say
you did that and you had half of a שיעור shiur of
each. Maybe, I'd have to think about that. Okay, anyway,
but... so again at the end of the day if it's all
within the same category it's not as much of a חידוש chidush
as we might have expected. Alright, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב חנינא אמר רב זירא וכן אמר רבי יאשיה
בר רבי חנינא. Amar Rav Chanina amar Rav Zeira v'chen amar Rabbi
Yoshiya bar Rabbi Chanina. So רב חנינא Rav Chanina said in the
name of רב זירא Rav Zeira and some say רבי יאשיה בר
רבי חנינא Rabbi Yoshiya bar Rabbi Chanina said.
Now what did he say actually? The key line he said is
missing from our text. It goes straight into the פסוק pasuk that
the גמרא Gemara is now going to quote as a challenge to
what he said, but it doesn't even say what he said. If
you look at the side, okay, now it might be he just
said he quoted this פסוק, pasuk, but again the מפרש mefaresh here
and תוספות Tosafot point to the גירסא girsa at the side of
the text. Let's look at the side on the right hand side
it says: וכן אמר רבי יאשיה בר רבי חנינא, v'chen amar Rabbi
Yoshiya bar Rabbi Chanina, whatever, דוקא דם שרץ ובשרו. davka dam sheretz
u'vassaro. Okay,
that the basic statement was that when do we say that the
blood and the flesh combine? If it's the same animal. Not a
blood and flesh of a different animal. Okay, that would not combine.
So if you have a little meat of one שרץ sheretz and
a little blood of another and they're sitting together, they do not
combine. Okay, דוקא דם שרץ ובשרו. davka dam sheretz uvesaro. Now we're
going to challenge it. מתיבי. meisivei. Okay, so now and now it's
מתיבי רבי יאשיה בר חנינא. meisivei Rabi Yoshi bar Chanina. Anyway, it's
a question who said what, but anyway here's the challenge of the
ברייתא. braisa. הטמאים, hatmeim, these are the things that are טמא, tamei,
מלמד שהן מצטרפין, melamed shehein mitztarpin,
that all of these טמא tamei things combine. ואפילו שרץ ושרץ, veafilu
sheretz vesheretz, even a piece of one שרץ sheretz and a piece
of another שרץ, sheretz, שרץ ודם, sheretz vedam, a שרץ sheretz and
blood, בין משם אחד בין משני שמות, bein misheim echad bein mishnei
shemos,
whether it's the same, like it's all the חולד, choled, whether it's
a little bit of a חולד choled and a little bit of
an עכבר. achbar. Okay, so they combine. Now if they're combining different
things and we said whether it's the meat or whether it's the
blood, presumably the meat of one and the blood of another
combine, even of a different type of an animal, and certainly not
the same animal itself.
So how do you deal with that if you say it has
to be the meat and the blood together? אמר רב יוסף, amar
Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, לא קשיא, lo kashya,
כאן בכולן כאן במקצתן. kan bechulan kan bemiktzasan.
It depends whether it's all of it or it depends whether it
is part of it. Now what does that mean?
One minute,
let me just check, I just want to double check one reading
of תוספות Tosafos here, one minute.
Yes, just
checking
because
he has a much better read than רש״י Rashi and I'm just
reminding myself what that read was. One
minute.
Right.
Okay, so here's right, so the way תוספות Tosafos reads רש״י Rashi
reads it, just to just so you should be aware, כאן בכולו
כאן במקצתו, kan bechulo kan bemiktzaso, that it depends whether the blood
is coming out of the whole thing or the blood is coming
out of a piece of it. If you have a piece of
the שרץ sheretz and the blood comes out from it, somehow because
it came out from only a piece of the animal, not the
whole animal, that makes it weaker and then it can't combine with
other things. If you have a dead rat or whatever, whatever is
an עכבר, achbar, and the blood comes out from the whole dead
rat, because it came out from the whole thing, it's more potent
and it can combine with other rats or other שרצים. shratzim. And
if it came out from like if it came out from a
half of the rat, the rat was broken into two and it
came out from half of it, that's what רש״י Rashi says. That's
a very hard read why that should at all make it different.
תוספות's Tosafos read, which is maybe a little bit more דחוק dachuk
in the words but is a lot more logical, says the point
here is what are you touching? When we
let's imagine that you had here, let's use this as my example,
here is my piece of meat, שרץ sheretz meat sitting in a
pile of blood, whether it's its own blood or some other blood,
okay? Now what am I touching? When we say it combines, am
I touching everything? Let's say both the meat and the blood? Or
am I just touching part of it, like just the meat or
just the blood? Okay. Now here's where he's saying when did I
say it matters if it's the blood of the same animal or
not? Because is it one unit or two units? That's what I'm
saying. So if you're just touching part, מקצתו, miktzaso, just the blood,
just the meat, if it's all is the blood of the animal
itself, it's all considered one unit and it's like you touched everything.
However, it is true it will combine with blood and meat of
another animal, but then they're separate units and then you have to
touch כולם, kulam, you have to touch both the meat and the
blood in order for to say you've touched the entire amount. Okay?
That's the way תוספות Tosafos reads it. It's a much cleaner read
than רש״י, Rashi, so that's how he reads it. כאן בכולו, kan
bechulo, let's read it again, כאן בכולו כאן במקצתו. kan bechulo kan
bemiktzaso.
If you touched all of it, they'll combine, blood and meat of
different things. If you only touched part, then it's only if it's
all from the same animal is it considered one unit. ומנא תימרא,
umana teimra, where do I get this idea? דתניא, detanya, we find
in the ברייתא, braisa,
this is in מסכת אהלות, Maseches Oholos, it's about blood of a
מת, meis, a corpse. נשפך על הרצפה, nishpach al haritzpa, it fell
on the floor, והיה מקומו קטפרס, vehaya mekomo katafres, and the place
it fell was like on an incline, and the blood was sort
of, running down on an incline. אהל על מקצתו טהור אהל על
כולו טמא. ohel al miktzaso tahor ohel al kulo tamei.
So I've got this incline and I've got blood running down it,
okay, and I put my hand over part of the blood, that's
I'm אהל ohel over the blood. Blood of a מת meis causes
טומאה. tuma. If it's only over part of the blood, I am
טהור. tahor. If I'm over all of the blood, then I am
טמא. tamei. Why? Because the logic is קטפרס אינו חיבור, katafres eino
chibur, that if it's on an incline, as opposed to if it's
flat, if it's on an incline, it's not considered to be connected.
The blood is not all seen as one unit as if it
puddles if it's flat. So therefore, since it's not connected, the only
way I can be טמא Tamei is if I'm over all of
it. But if I'm part of it, if it was all connected
and I'm part of it, then it's all one unit. Then I'm
מאהיל Ma'ahil and I'm טמא Tamei because it's not connected, I have
to be over all of it. Is that clear? If it's one
unit, you don't have to touch or be over all of it,
but if it's not one unit, then you do have to be
over all of it. Okay? So, מה מקצתה? Mai miktzata? What does
it mean מקצתה? miktzata? אילימא Eleima so anyway, the basic point it's
already really proven, which is is that when it's not one unit,
it does not suffice to be over only a part of it.
You have to be over all of it. מה מקצתה? Mai miktzata?
What does it mean part of it? אילימא מקצת דם? Eleima miktzat
dam? ואמר רבי חנינא אמר רבי רביעית דם שהגיס
בה טהורה Ve-amar Rabbi Chanina amar Rabbi revi'it dam she-higis bah tehorah
it so if it means hold on let me just check
תוספות. Tosafos.
Minute.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafos reads this that the question is מה מקצתה?
Mai miktzata? אילימא מקצת דם Eleima miktzat dam means if you say
מקצתה miktzata means that there isn't a full רביעית revi'it there, that
there's only again, some of these readings are not so great, but
תוספות Tosafos is trying to keep some of sort of make sense.
If you say מקצתה miktzata by this case about the blood means
that there's not even a full amount of blood there, מקצת דם.
miktzat dam. ואמר רבי חנינא אמר רבי Ve-amar Rabbi Chanina amar Rabbi
not a full amount there,
meaning it's not a רביעית. revi'it. Meaning, he's trying to prove that
when it's not one unit, you have to touch all of it.
Okay? And that's from the case of blood. Okay? When it's on
running on an incline, it's not one unit, you see you have
to touch all of it. He says, now don't tell me that
when it says מקצתה, miktzata, it means you don't have a full
amount there. Okay? That's not what it means. דהאמר רבי חנינא אמר
רבי רביעית דם שהגיס בה טהורה. De-ha-amar Rabbi Chanina amar Rabbi revi'it
dam she-higis bah tehorah. If you have a רביעית revi'it and you're
stirring, you're טהור. tahor. Why are you טהור tahor if you're stirring
it? What makes you stir? So תוספות Tosafos says that some of
the blood is getting absorbed into the spoon. So because some of
the blood you're stirring blood with a wooden spoon, some of it's
absorbed into the spoon, that makes it again considered not one unit
with the rest of the blood. So you see here again, you
have a case where you clearly have a רביעית, revi'it, but as
soon as it's not considered one unit, it's not enough to be
over part of it, you have to be over or touching all
of it.
Exactly. So אלא לאו שמע מינה כאן בכולו כאן במקצתה. Ela lav
shema minah kan be-kulo kan be-miktzatah. You see it matters whether you
are touching or being מאהיל ma'ahil over all of it or part
of it. שמע מינה. Shema minah. That's a good point. And again,
with is blood and the piece of a שרץ sheretz a one
unit or not, even if it's not on an incline, it's all
together, depends on whether it's from one animal or not from one
animal. שמע מינה. Shema minah. So the גמרא Gemara is happy with
that. Okay, now we get maybe the only interesting little, I don't
even know if you'd call it אגדתא, agadata, but I'll call it
a story in מסכת מעילה. Masechet Meilah. So let's take a look.
So let's take a look.
שאל רבי מתיא בן חרש Sha'al Rabbi Matya ben Charash בן חרש,
ben Charash, I think it is בן חרש ben Charash את רבי
שמעון בן יוחאי בעיר רומי. et Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai be-ir Romi.
So Rabbi Matya ben Charash asked Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai once when
they were in Rome. מנין לדם שרצים שהוא טמא? Minyin le-dam sheratzim
she-hu tamei? How do you know the blood of שרצים sheratzim causes
טומאה? tumah? We've been talking about does it combine with בשר. basar.
How do you know that it causes טומאה tumah altogether? אמר לו
דאמר קרא וזה לכם הטמא. Amar lo de-amar kra ve-zeh lachem ha-tamei.
And this is for you the טמא tamei בשרץ השרץ על הארץ
ba-sheretz ha-shoretz al ha-aretz that's an extra פסוק pasuk because anyway it
says אלה הטמאים לכם, eleh ha-tmei'im lachem, so that extra וזה לכם
ve-zeh lachem is to tell you even the blood is טמא. tamei.
Alright. אמרו לו תלמידיו Amru lo talmidav so the students of Rabbi
Matya ben Charash said to him חכים ליה בן יוחאי. Chakim lei
ben Yochai. Hey, Ben Yochai knows his got very smart. So he's
he's able to think for himself. He came up with his own
דרשה. drasha. Apparently this was at an early stage of Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai's career and they were very impressed that he got thought
of that himself. So אמר להם amar lahem so Rabbi Matya ben
Charash said back to his
students נומי תלמוד ערוך בפי של רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי. Numi talmud
aruch be-fi shel Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yosi. No, this is an
old tradition. He didn't come up with it himself. Maybe, you know,
well, also, why did he ask Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai if apparently
he's the senior rabbi here? So, you know, they're schmoozing and learning.
So he was just it wasn't like he didn't know the answer,
but he was opening a conversation. Okay, so apparently he knew the
answer. He said, yeah, don't give him too much credit. This is
already a well-established teaching of
רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי. Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yosi. And as we're
going to see, and he heard it from רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי.
Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yosi. And now we get how do you
know
this? שפעם אחת גזרה המלכות גזירה She-pa'am achat gazrah ha-malkhut gezeirah שלא
ישמרו את השבת. she-lo yishmeru et ha-Shabbat. One time there was an
edict. Right? Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai is the classic, I should say
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, when you normally just hear רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon in the משנה, Mishnah, it's Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Normally we
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai is this אגדית agadit figure, and we assume
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is somebody else. But סתם רבי שמעון stam
Rabbi Shimon in the משנה, Mishnah, תלמידי רבי עקיבא talmidei Rabbi Akiva
is Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So we're talking about in the period
of, you know, Rabbi Akiva and the immediate afterwards where it was
a real period of persecution. Okay, so one time the government, the
Roman government, made an
edict. I thought I said that.
Okay, what's I'm just afraid this is in the act of
yeah, I know, it's a little funny, right. I know, I understand.
Okay, so שבת, Shabbos, ברית מילה, Bris Milah, and טהרת המשפחה Taharas
HaMishpacha are pretty much the main identity things other than כשרות. Kashrus.
Yeah, I was gonna say, okay, כשרות. Kashrus. That was interesting. הלך
ראובן בן אסטרובלי. Halach Reuven ben Istrobli. So ראובן בן אסטרובלי Reuven
ben Istrobli clearly a more Hellenized name of his father and we'll
see that he obviously was some type of a figure within the
Roman
government.
וסיפר את קומי Ve-siper et kumi and he took and he did
this haircut called קומי, kumi, which is basically a type of a
haircut which was a Roman style of hair which was primarily not
worn by the Jews. And that actually is an interesting relevant גמרא
Gemara because according to some it might even be a לאו lav
to do this depending on how the hair was cut and speaks
about certain types of things which are allowed for people that have
to, you know, be in the position to have within the government
to influence for the betterment of the Jewish people. But anyway, so
he went and he got this haircut so that he would look
like a Roman noble person. והלך וישב עמהם, V'halach v'yashav imahem, and
he went and he sat, made it sound like what, in the
Senate or
something, in some type of a meeting. אמר להם, Amar lahem, and
he said to them: מי שיש לו אויב, Mi sheyesh lo oyev,
somebody who has an enemy, יעני או יעשר, ye'ani o ye'asher, does
he want the enemy to come poor or rich? אמרו לו, Ameru
lo, they said: יעני, ye'ani, they want him to come poor. אמר
להם, Amar lahem, אם כן, Im ken, לא יעשו מלאכה בשבת כדי
שיענו. lo ya'asu melacha b'shabbos kedei sheye'anu. So tell them not to
do מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos, they'll lose, you know, a lot
of their they'll lose fifteen percent of their productivity, so make them
poor. אמרו, Ameru, טביתא אמר, Tavita amar, you said good. בטלה לה
הדא גזירה, Batla let-ha-gizeira, let this גזירה gezeira be nullified. ובטלוה, Ubatlu'ah,
and they nullified. חזר ואמר להם, Chazar v'amar lahem, then he said:
מי שיש לו אויב, Mi sheyesh lo oyev, יכחיש או יברי? yachish
o yavri? Do you want your enemies to be weak or healthy?
אמרו לו, Ameru lo, יכחיש, yachish, they
said, weak. אמר להם, Amar lahem, אם כן, Im ken, ימולו בניהם
לשמונה ימים ויכחישון, yamolu b'nehem lishmona yamim v'yachishun, right? They can learn
from שמעון ולוי, Shimon v'Levi, you know that weakens them. ויכחישון, V'yachishun,
and that'll influence, that'll impact their health. אמרו, Ameru, they said: טביתא
אמר, Tavita amar, you said well. ובטלוה, Ubatlu'ah, and they got rid
of the גזירה gezeira of ברית מילה. Bris Milah. חזר ואמר להם,
Chazar v'amar lahem, then he said to
them: מי שיש לו אויב, Mi sheyesh lo oyev, ירבה או יתמעט?
yarbeh o yitma'et? You want them to be many or few? אמרו
לו, Ameru lo, יתמעט, yitma'et, few. So then they said, not knowing
exactly the biology here: אם כן, Im ken, לא יבעלו נידות. lo
yiv'alu niddos. Don't have sex when they're נידות, niddos, let them keep
that because then they'll have fewer kids. Not exactly getting the biology.
אמרו, Ameru, so they said: טביתא אמר, Tavita amar, you said well.
ובטלוה, Ubatlu'ah, and they nullified it. Then, הכירו בו שהוא יהודי. hikiru
bo shehu yehudi. He like pushed his luck a little too much.
Wait a minute, what did he make us do? We nullified everything!
So they realized he was a Jew. החזירו, Hecheziru, so they reinstated
all of the גזירות. gezeirot. So that's a lesson of don't push
your luck. Okay. אמרו, Ameru, then they
said: מי ילך ויבטל הגזירות? Mi yelech v'yavatel hagezeirot? Now the rabbis
said, who can we get
to try again, to try to reverse these edicts? ילך רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי. Yelech Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Let רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai go, שמלומד בנסים. shemelumad b'nissin. We know miracles
occur with him, like by the cave, right? He had all these
miracles. So, אין סומכין על הנס. ein somchin al hanes.
Well, here we have no choice, so might as well get somebody
who has a little bit more luck with
נסים. nissin. All right.
ואחריו מי ילך?
V'achrav
mi yelech?
Unless you don't do something, why a miracle to save you?
Right. Here you have no options. Now, of course רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai ran to the cave because he said
bad things about the Roman government, so
he's the last person I
would have asked him that, I understand. Okay. ואחריו מי ילך? V'achrav
mi yelech? Who will go after him, which presumably means I guess
אין סומכין על הנס
ein
somchin
al hanes well, it could mean if he doesn't succeed, but from
the continuation of the story it really seems like it means like
to accompany him. Who will accompany him? ומאן? U-man? What? I know,
but anyway, you'll see from the continuation of the story. So, רבי
אלעזר בר רבי יוסי. Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose. רבי אלעזר בר
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose, right, he's the one that's
gonna have taught about the דם שרות. Dam Sharot. What was that?
Okay, I don't know. He was somehow they thought he had influence.
אמר להם רבי יוסי, Amar lahem Rabbi Yose, so רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, רבי אלעזר בר רבי יוסי's Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose father,
said to the rabbis or whoever was deciding you know who to
send: ואילו היה אבא חלפתא קיים. V'ilu haya Abba Chalafta kayyam. If
אבא חלפתא Abba Chalafta was alive that was רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose
father יכולים אתם לומר לו תן בנך להריגה? yecholim atem lomar lo
ten bincha la-hariga? Would you tell my father to send me? Would
you be prepared to tell my father give your son over to
be killed? That's what's gonna happen if we go and we're not
successful. So you're asking me to send my son, רבי אלעזר בר
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose. How can you ask me
to do such a thing? So, אמר להם רבי שמעון, amar lahem
Rabbi Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said in response: Nu, אילו
היה יוחאי אבא קיים, ilu haya Yochai abba kayyam, יכולים אתם לומר
לו תן בנך להריגה? yecholim atem lomar lo ten bincha la-hariga? Would
you say to him, give your son over to be killed? It
sounds like he was concerned that, so now what exactly was רב
יוסי *Reb Yosi* concerned about? It sounds like he was concerned about
what's going to happen with the Roman government and רב שמעון בר
יוחאי Reb Shimon bar Yochai *Reb Shimon bar Yochai* said, I have
an equal reason to be concerned, but you know we got we
got to do it to save כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael*. But as
the story is going to continue, what רב יוסי *Reb Yosi* was
really more concerned about was not the Romans but רב שמעון בר
יוחאי Reb Shimon bar Yochai, *Reb Shimon bar Yochai*. So let's take
a look. We're going to take a look. So it says like
this, אמר amar: להו *amar lehu* רב יוסי *Reb Yosi*,
so רב יוסי *Reb Yosi* said to them, whoever the they were,
אנא אזיל *ana azil*, I'm going to go. Let me go instead
of my son. דילמא עניש ליה *dilma anish leih* רב שמעון Reb
Shimon, *Reb Shimon* because maybe רב שמעון Reb Shimon *Reb Shimon*, remember
רב שמעון Reb Shimon *Reb Shimon* was not the most easy-going character,
right? Remember he came out of the cave, you saw you know
he gave them the look, he burned them up.
So he was a very
like קנאי *kanai* type of a person. So he was afraid, he
was more afraid that on the way רב שמעון בר יוחאי Reb
Shimon bar Yochai. *Reb Shimon bar Yochai* would have so would get
something would bother him with his son and רב שמעון בר יוחאי
Reb Shimon bar Yochai *Reb Shimon bar Yochai* would do something to
his son, you know not necessarily physically but metaphysically or whatever. So
he that's what he was afraid about. So he said let me
go, I'd rather go than my son. But he still goes with
רב שמעון *Reb Shimon*. Right. Well he yeah, at least he could
say I you know I'm prepared myself you know it's more for
sure also.
And you mentioned it end up with רב שמעון *Reb Shimon* being
in the cave, the argument was between רב שמעון *Reb Shimon* and
רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda*, רב יוסי *Reb Yosi* was there and didn't
say anything. Aha. He kept his he had the sense to keep
his mouth shut.
That's a good point. So now maybe he's picking it up at
least for the when it's his own son that's at stake but
I forgot that רב יוסי *Reb Yosi* was the third party. Okay.
So he says let me
go, דילמא עניש
ליה *dilma anish leih* רב שמעון *Reb Shimon*, maybe רב שמעון *Reb
Shimon* will punish my son. דקמסתפינא *dekamistafina* and I'm afraid of that.
So קביל ליה דלא ליענשיה *kabil leih delo leiansheih*. רב שמעון *Reb
Shimon* said I promise I won't do anything against your son. And
according to the ירושלמי Yerushalmi, *Yerushalmi* I think he made a נדר
*neder* even. Okay, that he wouldn't do anything against his son. Yeah,
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* תוספות *Tosafot* quotes made a נדר *neder* that he wouldn't.
אפילו הכי ענשיה *afillu hachi ansheih*, but even so he didn't remember
the נדר *neder* and he wound up doing something to the to
punish the רב אלעזר בר רבי יוסי *Reb Elazar bar Reb Yosi*.
What happened? כשהיו מהלכין בדרך *keshehayu mahalchin baderech*, they were going on
their way, נישיילו שיילותא בפניהם *nishayalu sheilota bifnehem*, you know they're talking
in תורה *Torah*, what do you do when you're on the way
to Rome? So מניין לדם השרץ שהוא טמא *minayin ledam hasheretz shehu
tamei*, how do you know, they were asking how do we know
that דם השרץ *dam hasheretz* is טמא *tamei*? Back to that. עקם
פיו *ikam piv* רב אלעזר בר רבי יוסי *Reb Elazar bar Reb
Yosi*, רב אלעזר בר רבי יוסי *Reb Elazar bar Reb Yosi* like
like turned his mouth. What does this mean? So like רש"י *Rashi*
or the מפרשים *mefarshim* says like it sounds like he like you
know maybe tried to do a little ventriloquism, like answered it but
not make it clear that he was answering. תוספות *Tosafot* just says
it's a way of saying that he spoke up a little when
he shouldn't have, meaning רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Reb Shimon bar Yochai*
was apparently the senior and felt that it was in you know
don't give an answer, maybe one of the students, they weren't just
those two. Somebody asked that question and he jumped in and gave
the answer in the presence of רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Reb Shimon
bar Yochai* before רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Reb Shimon bar Yochai* could
give the answer. ואמר וזה לכם הטמא *veamar vezeh lachem hatamei*. אמר
amar, ליה *amar leih* רב שמעון *Reb Shimon*, so רב שמעון *Reb
Shimon* said to him, מעקימת שפתיך אתה אתה ניכר שתלמיד חכם אתה
*meakimat sefateicha attah attah nikar shetalmid chacham attah*, from your you know
from what from what you just said, your jumping up and speaking
or you know it's clear that you're a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*.
And אל יחזיר הבן אצל אביו *al yachzir haben etzel aviv*.
So let the son not return to the father. So which means
like yeah was pretty terrible. So you know again they say that
he was upset because if you take a look at תוספות *Tosafot*,
עקם פיו *ikam piv*, תוספות *Tosafot* says מיהר להשיב *miher lehashiv*, he
responded quickly. אל יחזיר הבן אצל אביו *al yachzir haben etzel aviv*,
ירושלמי מפרש דאחזו אסכרה *Yerushalmi mefaresh deachazu askara*, right which is what
is that? The croup or something? Some type of a of a
respiratory disease. וכשנזכר רב שמעון על שהתנה להשיבו אל אביו *ucheshenizkar Reb
Shimon al shehitnah lehashivo el aviv*, then he remembered that he had
sworn or made a נדר *neder* whatever, חזר ונתפלל עליו ונתרפא *chazar
venitpallel alav venitrapa* and in the end he got better. Okay but
he was so upset that you know you answered and you weren't
supposed to and this and that, somehow it was a פוגם *pogem*
in his כבוד kavod. *kavod*. But he made a statement about some
you know שתלמיד חכם אתה *shetalmid chacham attah*. Yeah it's clear you're
a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*. It's because you you know spoke up
when you shouldn't have. I know, yeah I also yeah the way
he's framed it it seems like it's a bash. That's right but
you jumped in when you shouldn't have and you shouldn't have you
shouldn't have. Right, right I know. But but what Michael is saying
is and why does he say ניכר שתלמיד חכם אתה *nikar shetalmid
chacham attah*? That's like even though you're a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*.
Like even though you're a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, right, you answered
but yeah. So anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is obviously not being
too sympathetic, touched down that if it's טמא *tamei* but it's okay
to harm somebody else but.
Well you think the you
think the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* in reporting this
story is sympathetic to רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Reb Shimon bar Yochai*?
No I don't know but the story is very problematic. Yes but
I would say
actually the opposite is that רב שמעון בר
יוחאי *Reb Shimon bar Yochai* got his
to some degree comeuppance because in the first story right it was
an exact parallel, they were walking and the and the older rabbi
asked and רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Reb Shimon bar Yochai* answered it's
exact parallel except...
of the positions are switched,
and he refused to give him the credit for the answer. He
said, yeah, sure, he
stole it from רב אלעזר בן רב יוסי. Reb Elazar ben Reb
Yosi So clearly רב שמעון בר יוחאי is not coming out good
here. Not only did he do this thing which he shouldn't have
and he swore not to and he reversed it or whatever, but
then in the end he himself repeated the mistake and the emphasis
was made that he stole this from somebody else, or not stole
or whatever, but it's not his own, he took it from somebody
else. So I think the whole point here is to discredit רב
שמעון בר יוחאי, not to validate what he did. That's the way
I read it. Yeah. Even the famous cave story, if you read
the whole thing, it's not exactly complimentary to רב שמעון, and the
real question is how is it that he's become the pinnacle of...
yeah, right. And it spoke about a moment of sympathy that he
had, right? He saw those זכור ושמור. Zachor v'Shamor. Right. Yeah. So
I don't think the גמרא is sympathetic to רב שמעון בר יוחאי.
Let's see the end of how he became such an iconic figure.
Right. That's true for the Kabbalists. Yeah. Definitely the whole cave and
as the Kabbalists, right. But I don't think in the גמרא, I
mean I think here it's clearly critical. Okay, so let's see the
end of the story. Okay. יצא לקראתו בן תמליון. Yatzah likrato Ben
Tamlayon. Now we have to still see how they got rid of
the גזירה. gezeirah. So בן תמליון Ben Tamlayon came and appeared to
them. This was like a type of a שד, shed, a type
of a demon. בן תמליון Ben Tamlayon is a demon? Yeah. And
he said to them רצונכם אבוא עמכם? Retzonchem avo imachem? Do you
want me to come with you and help you on your mission?
So בכה רב שמעון, bacha Reb Shimon, so רב שמעון cried and
אמר: מה שפחה של בית אבא, mah shifchah shel beis aba, the
maidservant of my father's house, meaning הגר, Hagar, נזדמן לה מלאך שלש
פעמים, nizdamen lah malach shalosh pe'amim, three times the angel appeared to
her, because every time the angel speaks to הגר, Hagar, it says
ויאמר לה מלאך השם,
Vayomer lah malach Hashem, ויאמר לה מלאך השם, Vayomer lah malach Hashem,
and חז"ל Chazal say it means that like a different angel was
sent each time. Three times she got an angel to appear to
her, ואני לא פעם אחת? va'ani lo pa'am achat? And yet for
me, I don't get any angels, I just get this demon. Okay,
so it once again shows that רב שמעון was very concerned about
his כבוד. So what happens? He says יבוא הנס מכל מקום. yavo
hanes mikol makom. All right, anyway, let the miracle come however it
has to come. I'd prefer it be an angel. It has to
come through you, let it come through you. קדים הוא, Kadim hu,
so this demon went ahead על ברתיה דקיסר, al barta deKeisar, inserted
himself, possessed the daughter of the Caesar. Okay, so she became possessed.
כי מטא התם, Ki mata hatam, so when רב שמעון בר יוחאי
got there, אמר, so he said, presumably this is a shortened version
of the longer story in the ירושלמי, but you know, the demon
was sort of saying that it was possessing the Caesar's daughter, said
like yo, בן יוחאי Ben Yochai is needed, בן יוחאי, Ben Yochai,
somehow it was very clear that it had to be בן יוחאי
Ben Yochai to come and solve the problem. And then when he
got there, he said בן תמליון צא, Ben Tamlayon tzei, בן תמליון
צא, Ben Tamlayon tzei, that was what he muttered. Okay, וכיון, vekeivan,
and then he left, and then he solved, he did the exorcism.
וכיון דקרי ליה, Vekeivan dekarei lei, once he called out בן תמליון
Ben Tamlayon's name, נפיק, nafik, he left, אזל, azal, and he went
away. אמר להון, Amar lahon, so he said to them, he the
Caesar or the people from the Caesar's household said to them, שאלו
כל מה דאית לכון למשאל, sha'alu kol mah de'is lechon lemishal, whatever
you want, ask for anything, it's yours. עיילינו לגנזיה לשקול כל דבר,
Ayileinu leginzei lishkol kol davar, they brought them into the treasure house
to take whatever they wanted. אשכחו ההוא אגרתא, Ashkechu hahu igrata, they
found that edict, you know, that letter, that proclamation that made the
גזירה. gezeirah. שקלוה, Shakluha, they took it, וקרעוה, vekare'uha, and they tore
it up, and that way they reversed the edict. והיינו דאמר רב
אלעזר בן רב
יוסי,
Ve-hainu de-amar Reb Elazar ben
Reb
Yosi, now remember of course that רב אלעזר בן רב יוסי Reb
Elazar ben Reb Yosi was there with him.
So we have another statement of רב אלעזר בן רב יוסי that
we're tying into this story. What's the other statement? He says when
they were talking about the פרוכת parochet that they did the sprinkling
of the blood, you know, on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So he
said אני ראיתיה בעיר רומי, ani re'isiha be-Ir Romi, I saw the
פרוכת parochet from this destroyed בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash in Rome, והוו
עליה כמה טיפי דמים, vehavu alei kama tipu damim, there were some
sprinkles of blood. Wow, when did he see it? He saw it
when he was brought into the treasure house in Rome. Now, you
know, it's like people saying they wonder what's in the Vatican's warehouse,
so here what's in the Rome treasure house. Someone said אני ראיתיה
ב... ani re'isiha be... I don't know, I don't know. So we
will end with here anyway ties into this week's פרשה parshah of
course which is אחרי מות Acharei Mos and the sprinkling of blood.